# Tim Weigel

timweigel@gmail.com Please contact me for full contact information.

## **Profile**

I'm a skilled data professional with over a decade of SQL Server experience as well as Salesforce migration and integration knowledge. I'm enthusiastic, and a fast learner. I'm process-oriented, careful, methodical, and thorough. I ask questions when I need to, and my research skills are top-notch. I document my work. I'm an active part of the SQL Server community.

# Experience

SAAS CONSULTING GROUP; AUSTIN, TX (REMOTE) – MARCH 2021 - PRESENT DATA TECHNICAL LEAD, JANUARY 2024 - PRESENT

Propose, develop, and implement data migration processes and procedures, and coding standards in a collaborative environment with data leads and management. Develop and implement standard configurations of migration SQL Server environments for projects of varying scales.

Own and maintain process and technical documentation for the Data Practice in an Atlassian Confluence environment.

Mentor junior data consultants, providing guidance on problem-solving, T-SQL coding, and SQL Server configuration. Serve as a resource for the Data Practice on T-SQL coding practices and solutions.

**DATA PRACTICE MANAGER, AUGUST 2021 - DECEMBER 2023** 

Oversaw day-to-day data practice operations including resource allocation and consumption reviews, scheduling, and time tracking oversight.

Championed allocating internal development time for development of a Salesforce-based data mapping tool, which led to significant improvements in data mapping quality and reductions in migration development times.

SENIOR SALESFORCE DATA CONSULTANT, MARCH 2021 - AUGUST 2021

Developed and implemented data migration solutions using DBAmp and SQL Server for complex data transformations into Salesforce.

SENIOR DATABASE ADMINISTRATOR, INTRADO; MOBILE, AL – JUNE 2020 - MARCH 2021

Oversaw SQL Server configurations, deployment, and performance tuning. Resolved outages.

Conducted audits, optimized resource utilization, and implemented improved monitoring processes.

Mentored junior and mid-career DBAs, helping them plan, learn, and develop as data professionals. Provided guidance to management and stakeholders on best practices and procedures for deploying and maintaining a complex SQL Server estate.

SQL SERVER DBA, NATIONAL MULTIPLE SCLEROSIS SOCIETY; DENVER, CO (REMOTE) – MARCH 2018 - MAY 2020

Member of the team that planned and executed the migration of NMSS's internal CRM platform to Salesforce's Nonprofit Success pack, including vendor selection for the Enterprise Service Bus platform.

Wrote the foundational documents for a cloud-first architecture plan, advocating for transitions to scalable PaaS solutions for data storage, analytics, and data science.

Developed and implemented a bulk copy-based approach for data import, resulting in significant runtime reduction, and implemented change tracking functionality for integration processing.

Managed maintenance, troubleshot performance issues, resolved outages, managed security across SQL Server environments, and supported SQL Server Integration Services and SQL Server Reporting Services.

Implemented performance monitoring improvements.

SENIOR DATABASE ADMINISTRATOR, PGI; COLORADO SPRINGS, CO – NOVEMBER 2016 - MARCH 2018 Conducted SAN consolidation, reviewed Active Directory group membership, and built a disaster recovery environment.

Managed maintenance, troubleshot performance issues, resolved outages, and supported replication across systems and regions.

Developed pilot plan for migrating critical systems from SQL Server 2005 and SQL Server 2008 to SQL Server 2014, including SAN changes, cluster upgrades, and database movement.

Mentored junior DBAs, helping them plan, learn, and develop as data professionals.

## Education

COLORADO COLLEGE, COLORADO SPRINGS, CO - BA ASIAN STUDIES, 2006

Graduated Cum Laude, recipient of the Excellence in Asian Studies award. Member of Phi Beta Kappa β of Colorado.

### Skills

SQL Server ecosystem administration, including backups, consistency checks, and index maintenance, SQL Server Integration Services and SQL Server Reporting Services management and troubleshooting, database planning and architecture, high-availability and disaster recovery planning and implementation including clustering, database replication, and performance monitoring and tuning

Salesforce data model and data migration

Business process development

Compliance audits

# SQL Server Community Involvement

WIREGRASS SQL & DATA COMMUNITY; DOTHAN, AL – 2020

Founded the Wiregrass SQL & Data Community in early 2020 to provide learning and networking opportunities to the underrepresented data community in the Wiregrass region encompassing Dothan, AL and surrounding counties.

Secured PASS affiliation, meeting space through the Dothan Houston County Library System, set up social media accounts on Twitter, Facebook, and LinkedIn to conduct communication and marketing, and conducted marketing activities through various social media channels.

COLORADO SPRINGS SQL SERVER USERS GROUP; COLORADO SPRINGS, CO – 2016 - 2018 VICE PRESIDENT OF MEMBERSHIP, JANUARY 2017 - DECEMBER 2018

Managed group membership and engaged in outreach activities to maintain and increase group membership.

VICE PRESIDENT OF MARKETING, JANUARY 2016 - DECEMBER 2016

Revived the group's dormant Twitter and Facebook accounts and implemented a social media strategy to increase group engagement. Coordinated email communication with

group members about upcoming events and community news. Collaborated with our sponsors to ensure their messages reached our membership, leading to several staffing agencies increasing their sponsorship of our group.

Assisted with planning and running multiple SQL Saturday events. Repeatedly succeeded in increasing the number of sponsors for the events, bringing new sponsors on board for 2016 and 2017. Participated in speaker vetting and selection, and event schedule planning. Coordinated volunteer engagement, overseeing volunteer staff. Participated actively in event setup and teardown.

#### **TALKS**

#### **CHANGE TRACKING METHODS IN SQL SERVER**

SQL Saturday Denver – September 2018 Denver SQL Server Users Group – April 2018 SQL Saturday Colorado Springs – March 2018

### **TEMPDB MANAGEMENT**

Denver SQL Server Users Group – April 2017 Colorado Springs SQL Server Users Group – February 2017

### CHANGE DATA CAPTURE

MagicPASS (Remote, Orlando, FL) – April 2017 Colorado Springs SQL Server Users Group – September 2015

### **CHANGE TRACKING**

Colorado Springs SQL Server Users Group – October 2016